<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Duke of Saxonie his iubilee with a short chronologie. Both shewing the goodnesse of God, in blessing the Gospel of Christ, since Luther first opposed the Popes pardons.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842262</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842262</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6903</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04534)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 754:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Duke of Saxonie his iubilee with a short chronologie. Both shewing the goodnesse of God, in blessing the Gospel of Christ, since Luther first opposed the Popes pardons.</title>
                  <author>Johann Georg I, Elector of Saxony, 1585-1656. aut</author>
                  <author>W. S., fl. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface initialed: W.S.</note>
                  <note>"The Duke of Saxonie his iubilee" signed: Iohannes George, Churfurst, that is, Prince Elector.</note>
                  <note>Proclaiming a celebration of the jubilee of one hundred years since Luther posted his theses--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalog.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformation --  Anniversaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:1"/>
            <p>THE DVKE OF SAXONIE HIS IVBILEE: <hi>With</hi> A SHORT CHRONOLOGIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BOTH</hi> Shewing the goodneſſe of God, in bleſſing the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, ſince LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER <hi>firſt oppoſed the Popes</hi> Pardons.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel 6.2. &amp; 19.11, 13, 19, 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I ſaw, and behold, a white horſe, and he that ſate on him, had a bow, and a Crowne was giuen vnto him, and he went forth conquering, and to conquer.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by WILLIAM IONES dwelling in Red-croſſe-ſtreete. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader; It is an abhorred cuſtome of the Synagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> to publiſh <hi>common prayers</hi> in a ſtraunge tongue: it would be (at leaſt) a blame worthy ouerſight in theſe our home planted Churches of Chriſt not to publiſh <hi>common prayſes</hi> in our vulgar tongue. The former taketh away the poſsibility of ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> with our owne ſpirits: the latter neglecteth a iuſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of finging a ioynt (though as yet an earthly) <hi>Halelu-iah</hi> with Gods Saintes: Receiue therefore here offered to thine hands <hi>common praiſes</hi> in thy propper language, to wit, a <hi>Iubile</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in <hi>Saxonie,</hi> &amp; by the tranſlation of a worthy Miniſter in our London Dutch Church, made a reioycing aſſumed in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> Were it not tranſlated, it could not be vnderſtood, were it not vnderſtood it could not be a reioycing to the Engliſh, which get it ought to be, becauſe it miniſtreth matter of praiſes to God common to them with the Dutch. Our rule willeth it ſhould be common. For when the <hi>Proper</hi> in <hi>(Pſal. 102.)</hi> had made it a note of all Gods ſeruants that <hi>they take pleaſure in the ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Zion,</hi> and a promiſe of their Maiſter that <hi>he would build vp Zion,</hi> he concludeth in <hi>Pſal. 18.</hi> that <hi>This ſhall be written for the generations to come, and the people which ſhall be created ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi> Now wee and all Gods people whereſoeuer, make vp all but one body, the Church (which is <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) the requickening and recollecting of whoſe members was in part, by <hi>Luther</hi> effected: we haue all but one head, Chriſt, the functions of whom, and ſole effecacy of whoſe merits were by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> cleared, and defended: we haue all but one Faith &amp; Goſpell, which in fundamentall pointes was by <hi>Luther</hi> profeſſed, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated. Seeing therefore this requickening of the Churches members, this defence of Chriſts merits, this profeſsion of the true Faith made in the beginning of the next preceding age are
<pb facs="tcp:6903:3"/>
here ioyfully recognized let that promiſe of the rearing of <hi>Zion,</hi> once written, now performed, ſtirre vp vs the generations follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>England</hi> as well as in <hi>Germany,</hi> to praiſe the Lord. Hereby ſhall we ſhew the feeling of fellow members, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saint-like beleeuers in preferring <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> aboue our chiefeſt ioy: <hi>Pſal. 137.6.</hi> Adde we to our rule commanding, the examples of others prouoking to make this matter of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing common. Diuerſe other partes of <hi>Germany</hi> in a godly imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation haue Iubilized with <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and in ſome places, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath cauſed new coynes to be ſtamped with ſentences compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the letters numerall of the yeere. <hi>1617.</hi> terminating the Age ſince <hi>Luther</hi> firſt ſet vp his propoſitions. Theſe let vs follow howſoeuer, perhaps, not in stamping the letters of the yeere v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our coynes, yet in imprinting the glad tidings thereof in our hearts. You ſee (gentle reader) that this Iubile ought to bee common: now that it may be more common, vnderſtand that it is Chriſtian. Here is not any Popiſh rite, ſauouring of iudaiſme, thruſt vpon any of the Churches. For why? <hi>Rome,</hi> in an apiſh (becauſe vnwarranted) imitation of the Iewiſh Church, retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yeares of Iubile as a perpetuated rite of the Goſpell: the Churches of Chriſt doe not ſo: <hi>Rome</hi> appointeth ſtate or ſet times for her Iubilies: the Churches of Chriſt doe not ſo. This preſented Iubile of <hi>Saxonie</hi> is my warrant. The occaſion whereof was taken from a prophecy currantly receiued among the Papiſts (though as blinde in the vttering, as falſe in the euent) namely, that <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine ſhould breath out its laſt, with the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of an hundreth yeeres. Which being layed and weighed in the ballance by the Chriſtian Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and other Princes, together with their owne experimentall knowledge of the now more then euer, flouriſhing and roote-taking of the doctrine of the Goſpell both throughout <hi>Germany,</hi> and in other countries, they not onely founde that Prophecy to light and the Prophets therof vaine, but alſo thought fit, by way of an holy Triumph, and Feaſt (as it were) of ſhouting, thankefully to ſolemnize the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their manumiſsion from the thraldome of Antchriſt, by the hand of God vpon <hi>Luther,</hi> and through <hi>Luther</hi> iuſt an hundreth yeeres before. So that the occaſion &amp; time hereof being
<pb facs="tcp:6903:3"/>
of ſo extraordinary nature, no doubt but God is hereby much glorified, in that by the ſame the hearts of his people are more quickened to the more affectionate embracino of his truth ſo graciouſly continued And here, if thou wilt giue me leaue I will aduenture to make a ſurer Prophecy then thr Papiſts did, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſecond comming of Mahomet for the ſtrengthening of the Turkiſh Infidel, and the exterpation of <hi>Luthers</hi> purer doctrine for the confirming of the Popiſh, ſhall fall out both in a yeere. When this will bee, let the Pope enquire of the Muſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in meane time that I preſage truely bee thou pleaſed to gather out of the Preface of a learned man in <hi>Scotland</hi> before the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> his reaſons of departure or there printed. Which, being full of moſt worthy obſeruations helping to fill vp the meaſure of our ioy, I haue hereunto prefixed. Neither haue I onely prefixed theſe, as helping to fill, but alſo adioyned to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, celebrated in the laſt, a <hi>Chronologie</hi> continued yeerely from the firſt of that hundreth ſince <hi>Luther,</hi> as fulfilling that meaſure of ioy. This was penned in Latine by ſtudents in <hi>Worms</hi> and printed at <hi>Heidelberge</hi> and now tranſlated into Engliſh. For a more cleare inſight into the proſperous ſucceſſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, therein but touched, I referre thee to an Oration of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend and learned, <hi>Scultetus</hi> made in the <hi>Arch-Palatine</hi> Court, and called a <hi>Secular Sermon.</hi> Now this <hi>Chronoligy,</hi> I ſay, fulfilleth our ioy, in that whereas among the Iewes fifty yeeres fourtie nine were of <hi>ſeruice,</hi> the laſt onely of <hi>releaſing,</hi> euery one of our hundreth aſſureth vs of the releaſe of ſome either Churches or Perſons, from <hi>Romes</hi> Aegiptian bondadge and Babiloniſh captiuitie, howſoeuer in (indeede) <hi>Marke-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie de Dominis</hi> may well make the laſt notoriouſly ſolemne. This in breife of the Goſpells Iubile, with a word more of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, I will conclude. The Papiſts (forſooth) hearing of this Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing of Chriſt his Churches thought it ſtood not with the policy of there kingdome to ſit ſtill leaning on their elbowes, and hanging their eares. How then? They put good faces on it, force out a laughter; and celebrate a <hi>Iubile.</hi> Did they not feare, may we thinke, that the report of our ioyfull releaſe would cauſe many to free themſelues from their bonds? But ſee we what the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate.
<pb facs="tcp:6903:4"/>
               <hi>A Iubilee,</hi> ſurely but <hi>verba-tenus</hi> in name onely, <hi>reate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in nature, a Faſt. Yea, <hi>Simulatum Iubelaeum fit duplex jeiunium:</hi> Their Iubile fained makes their Faſt doubled. Wherefore I may apply that to the Synagogue of Rome which the Poet ſpake of another, <hi>Spem vultu ſimulat, prem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t alto corde dolorem,</hi> Whilſt hope in face ſits counterfeit, heart-preſſing greife makes pulſes beate. Behold their Iubile which ſhould argue ioy; and ioy the Spirits dilatation, is become a <hi>Faſt,</hi> whoſe aſſociate is greife, and greifes the Spirits compreſſion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their clapping of handes is nought elſe but wringing of hands; their ſhoutings, groanings; their releaſe, bondage; their feaſtings, faſtings. And iuſtly may they ſo do. For ſuch faſting is to them a ſigne that our bridegrome Chriſt is not among them: for if the Bridgrome were with them how could they mourne? <hi>Mat. 9, 15.</hi> But I deſire they may ſtill mourne, and be inwardly vexed not ſo much for the downefall of their abhominations, as for their abhominations themſelues, and doe thou (good Reader) take vp with me in their behalfe the prayer of the Prophet <hi>Pſal. 83.19. Fill their faces with ſhame O Lord, that they may know thy name.</hi> This is the worſt I wiſh them, with which and mine earneſt wiſhes to thee that thou wouldeſt clappe hands with thoſe in exultation with whom thou art to claſpe handes in holy profeſſion, I leaue theſe treatiſes to thy view, and thy ſelfe to the watchfull eye of Gods prouidence: <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Preface ſet before the Arch-biſhop <hi>of Spalato his Reaſons of Departure, printed</hi> in Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eceiue (Chriſtian Reader) a proofe of the force of Truth, and a preſage of the end of that worke God is about to doe in theſe laſt Ages: A man brought vp in the Learning of Egypt, and enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Sorceries of Babel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe or counſell of any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, by occaſion of Popiſh Tyrannie, ſearching the trueth, findeth out their error in Doctrine, and abuſes in Diſcipline: and conuinced of both, firſt in his mind forſaketh their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and now in his body fleeth from their ſocietie. This is not like to the change of <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> and <hi>Arrius</hi> of olde, or of <hi>Carrier</hi> in our time, whoſe miſcontented humour, for hopes diſappointed, made them alter their opinion: But more like to that of <hi>Paulus Vergerius</hi> Biſhop of Iuſtinople, whom vniuſt ſuſpitions at the firſt burdened with a ſecret fauour of Lutheraniſme: for purging whereof he intended a refutation of <hi>Luthers</hi> Doctrine. But while hee wrangled with the Truth, to ouercome it, he was taken captiue of it; and leauing his place and dignities, rendred himſelfe at Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to our Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The ground of our preſage, is Gods truth in times accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, wherein Prouidence goes on with remarkeable degrees of perſons, and places, not without ſome reſpect to the Periods of time. He raiſed <hi>Wickleff</hi> from their Schooles, <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> from their Pulpits, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> from their
<pb facs="tcp:6903:5"/>
Cloyſters, and now <hi>Marke Antony</hi> from their Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Chaire. The places haue the like gradation: Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeemeth too farre from Rome, to waken them by <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kleffs</hi> crie: therefore it founded nearer in Germanie. And now Dalmatia looking ouer the Venetian Gulfe, aſſureth Italy, that her next Aduertiſer ſhall bee within her bowels. It was more than a Poeticall Licence to apply <hi>Sybilla's</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Chriſt to <hi>Saloninus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Pollio,</hi> for keeping in memorie his victorie, in taking in Salonas. But this our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loninus</hi> maketh large reſtitution, and applieth the Oracles of God to the owne purpoſe: As the Clergie hath gone before, ſo Princes doe follow: The King of Great Brittaine, with moſt of the Princes of Germany, ſtand out already againſt Rome: the ambiguitie of France will reſolue in the end in an open departure: and the temporizing of Venice impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth more the want of occaſion, than of will and reſolution. The Romane Empire did ſtretch out it ſelfe by degrees, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the mids to the extremities, as circles goe out from the Center: and at the extremities againe their ruine began, and went backe to the heart. The fall of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Monarchy ſhall keepe the ſame courſe.</p>
            <p>The Periods of time haue their owne obſeruation. The Iewiſh ſolemnitie of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> not brought into the Church till the thirteenth Age, was then tyed to the Centenarie number: and that their ioy hath ſince proued to bee like the ſong of the Marmaid before a ſtorme: for ſoone after, <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kleffe</hi> began to trouble their mirth: and in the end of that Age <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> made them ſome more buſineſſe, till in the 1415. yeere, the holy Fathers, at Conſtance by a Punicke faith, brought him to the fire. An hundred yeeres after him, <hi>Luther</hi> renewed his ſong with greater boldneſſe, and in the 1517. yeere gaue out his Propoſitions againſt the Pope: from which time they haue perſwaded themſelues, and euen to this day aſſure their followers, that <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine can ſtand no longer then an hundred yeeres. This preſent yere cloſeth that Period: and while they looke for an euaniſhing of that Doctrine, behold, euen from themſelues it receiueth
<pb facs="tcp:6903:5"/>
againe a new light, a new teſtimonie. Wee hold with <hi>Plato</hi> the fatalitie of Periods, but <hi>Pythagoras</hi> numbers are too weake a ground for ſuch a neceſſitie: or if we ſhall take any numbers, it muſt be theſe of ſinne; and in ſinne, more the degrees then the numbers: The Amorites ſinnes muſt come to the height, and the Iewes muſt fill their cup before their puniſhment. The Phariſees of our time doe mightily to fill out their meaſure. The pride and filthines of Sodom, the whoredomes of Babel are now multiplied exceedingly; and the greateſt ſinne, euen that to death, is become an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemicke diſeaſe among their Clergie. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the truth, <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. can ſcoffe at it, <hi>Gardinerus</hi> can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it at his death, but with this addition: That it muſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill be impugned, then the ſtate of Rome decay. All their wits runne vpon this one point, but all their meanes turne vpon them. The crueltie of their inquiſition, the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of their Prohibitions, their impudencie in falſifying words and writs, giue them but a moments aduantage. But euen from theſe ſhall come their ruine. A lie hath no more ſtrength than for the time it is ſpoken and credulouſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: but the eternall force of Truth hath more than a moment any preuailing. What then reſteth for them, but that they giue place to the fatalitie of their eſtate, ſince they will not giue place to the Truth. And for vs, while Rome is renting in it ſelfe, take heed that we be not diuided. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer now caſteth the apple of ſtrife into the Reformed Church, proueth an enemie to God, and an improfitable friend to Antichriſt. Let vs ſtand ſtill, and behold the work of the Lord, and be ſure, while we imagine we haue left Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, that we haue firſt forſaken Egypt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:6"/>
            <head>THE DVKE OF SAXONIE HIS IVBILEE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt wee make no doubt, but that every Chriſtian and good loving heart doth duely eſteeme what a high and great worke of Grace it is, that Almighty God, in theſe latter dayes, and on the late eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world (after ſo long and miſerable darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bondadge) hath brought us unto the cleare light of the bleſſed Goſpell, and Chriſtian Libertie, and hath preſerved us hetherto, in the middeſt of the manifold rage and boiſterouſneſſe of the Devill and his Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>We muſt therefore acknowledge, that we are in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bound, even from the bottome of our ſoules to laud, prayſe, and honor the High Maieſtie of God, for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee haue concluded, with leaue of the Higheſt to celebrate a ſolemne feaſt of <hi>Iubilee.</hi> For, if the corporall deliuerance of the Iſraelites out of Egypt was of ſuch waight and worth, that many hundred yeeres thereafter, the ſaid deliuerance was moſt gloriouſly extolled: Then it is more expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6903:7"/>
that the ſpirituall deliuerance from the Romiſh Antichriſtian bondage bee celebrated with ioy and thankſgiuing.</p>
            <p>Wee will therefore, firſt, That this feaſt of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> on the 26. day of October 1617. be publiſhed from the pulpit in our Lands and Dominions vnto our people, admoniſhing them vnto a ſerious and hearty meditation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we will that on the 30. of October, in the afternoone in euery Pariſh Church, at the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed houre, the <hi>Veſper</hi> be ſung, and the <hi>Confeſsion</hi> read, as is done on other high Feſtiuall dayes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we ordaine, that on the 31. of October, (on the which, an hundred yeeres before, that deare and worthy inſtrument of God, M. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> of bleſſed memorie, did ſet vp his firſt diſputation againſt that ſhameleſſe and impudent Popiſh ſhop of <hi>Indulgences</hi>) two Sermons ſhall be made, one before, the other after Noone: likewiſe on the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of Nouember, and on the ſaid three dayes, the holy Supper of the Lord ſhall be diſtributed, and the Miniſters ſhall admoniſh their hearers to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how Almightie God by the ſaid reformation hath giuen vnto them, the right vſe of his moſt holy Teſtament, and hath deliuered his Church from the manifold abuſes of the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the Villages where there is no Preacher, on the firſt and ſecond of Nouember onely, ſhall bee made a Sermon in the fore-noone time, and in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone may bee ſung and read the wonted <hi>Veſper,</hi> or Euening prayer.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, whereas the cuſtome beareth in our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6903:7"/>
Churches, that on Feſtiuall dayes and Fridayes, the ordinarie Text, (which is called the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> and <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi>) is read before the Sermon: We will, that on the 31. of October, in ſtead of the Epiſtle, bee read the 76. Pſalme, with this admonition:</p>
            <p>Dearely beloued, heare with attention, and due reuerence the 76. Pſalme, wherein the moſt High is praiſed, that he hath made himſelfe knowne aright vnto his people, and hath defended the ſame, in the true diuine ſeruice againſt the furious rage of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And the people is admoniſhed to teſtifie and ſhew their obedience and thankfulnes vnto the Lord their God.</p>
            <p>The words of the Pſalme are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Iuda is God knowne, his Name is great in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſtead of the Goſpel, ſhall bee read the 12. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the holy Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> with this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            <p>Dearely beloued, heare with attention and due reuerence, the 12. Chapter of the holy and high-il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> wherein is clearely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, not onely how Antichriſt, (whom the holy Ghoſt deſcribeth vnder the name of <hi>Antiochus</hi>) that is the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſhould doe and deale according vnto his pleaſure, ſhould exalt himſelfe ouer all that is called <hi>God,</hi> ſhould make no account of the honeſt loue of women, nor alſo of God; ſhould honour a Maſſe-God (called <hi>Mauſim</hi>) as his God, ſhould ſeduce much people with the oblation of great gifts: But alſo, how Almighty God in due time, by a ſound of the morning and mid-night would terrifie and aſtoniſh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6903:8"/>
him: Which is brought to paſſe by that worthy man and inſtrument of God, Doctor <hi>Luther,</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memorie, one hundred yeeres agoe.</p>
            <p>The words of the chapter are theſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On Friday the firſt of Nouember, wee ordaine in ſtead of the Epiſtle, the 87. Pſalme: and to propound the ſame vnto the Congregation, as followeth:</p>
            <p>Dearly beloued, heare with attention and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, the foureſcore and ſeuenth Pſalme, wherein is worthily exalted, the glorie of Gods Church, how the moſt High loueth the ſame, how firme the ſame is grounded, what worthy things are preached in the ſame in all Languages, with ioy and exultation. All which things by Gods ſingular grace are to bee found in our Euangelicall Churches.</p>
            <p>The words of the Pſalme are theſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of the Goſpel, ſhall be read a part of the 14. Chapter of the Reuelation of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> from the ſixth verſe vnto the 13. <hi>excluſiuè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dearely beloued, heare with due attention and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, a part of the 14. Chapter of the Reuelation of S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> Wherin the holy Ghoſt manifeſtly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth, how in the laſt dayes, (after that Antichriſt had raged a long time with great fierceneſſe,) Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God would ſend an Angell, that is to ſay, an Euangelicall Teacher, Preacher and Reformer, who ſhould declare vnto all kind of Nations an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Goſpel; and by the ſaid preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that great citie <hi>Babylon,</hi> (which is, the Romiſh Poperie) ſhould be deſtroyed, whereof the ſaid Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſhould giue beforehand a faithfull warning. All which, is richly brought to paſſe and accompliſhed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6903:8"/>
one hundred yeeres agoe, by Doctor <hi>Luther</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memorie, and his faithful followers the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Diuines, Teachers, and Preachers in many kingdomes, Electoratſhips, Dukedomes, Lands and Dominions, but chiefly in Germany.</p>
            <p>The words of the text are theſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Concerning the third Feſtiuall day, whereas the ſame falleth on the 20. Sunday <hi>Trinitatis,</hi> the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed Epiſtle and Goſpel may be read, becauſe that out of both ſuch matter can be drawen and handled, which is fit for the preſent time of <hi>Iubilee</hi> Feaſt.</p>
            <p>Yet if any one is deſirous, in the morning or eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sermon to expound ſome other Text, we leaue it to his diſcretion; whether it be the 46 or 48. Pſal. or the 13. chapter of Exodus, verſ. 3. or the 14. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid Booke, or the 16. chapter of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation, or ſome part of the 17. or 18. or any other fit ſentence.</p>
            <p>But on the 31. of October, and 1. of Nouember the appointed Pſalmes and Leſſons ſhall be read and declared in the Sermon.</p>
            <p>Yet if any high-graduated Diuines pleaſe to draw from ſome other Text their <hi>Meditationes Iubilaeas,</hi> we in our gracious fauour wil admit the ſame.</p>
            <p>Fiftly we ordaine, that good order be kept in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: and we doubt not but that in our Cities, the Superintendents and Preachers, wil ordain the figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Muſicke. Beſides, we hold it fit and profitable for the common people, to cauſe before and after the Sermon, thoſe ſongs to be ſung, which are beſt knowne vnto them, both for voyce and matter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6903:9"/>The firſt words of the ſongs are theſe:
<q>
                  <l>Lord God we praiſe thee, Lord God we thanke thee.</l>
                  <l>Now praiſe the Lord my ſoule.</l>
                  <l>Glorie be onely vnto the higheſt God.</l>
                  <l>Our God is a firme and ſtrong tower.</l>
                  <l>If our God were not with vs when our enemies rage.</l>
                  <l>O Lord thy godly Word hath long bin kept in darkneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Preſerue vs, O Lord, by thy Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly wee ordaine, that the Common prayer of Confeſſion be not read on this Feaſt: But wee haue giuen order to ſet downe a certaine forme of prayer, and thankſgiuing, whereby the Higheſt is praiſed for his gracious and powerfull deliuerance out of the cruel Egyptiacal bondage: And againe, is pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that by his omnipotencie (as hitherto, ſo for the time to come) it would pleaſe him, to conſerue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs the pure and ſauing Goſpel, and the right vnderſtanding and vſe of the holy Sacraments, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all dammageable errours and hereſies, for vs and our heires. Beſides, it is ordered, to pray that it would pleaſe God from time to time to giue Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Dukes and Magiſtrates, and to grant vnto thoſe that now are, a long life and bleſſed welfare, both temporall and eternall.</p>
            <p>We will, that theſe our Ordonances ſhall be duly obſerued without contradiction, in all our cities and villages, by the Superintendents, Miniſters, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and all the Inhabitants of our Countries and Dominions.</p>
            <p>And concerning our two Vniuerſities <hi>Leipſich</hi> and <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> we hold it fit and expedient, that the Theologicall facultie, employ the whole weeke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6903:9"/>
after the 2. of Nouember, in exquiſite Diſputations and Orations, comprehending therein the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of former darknes, of the enſuing gracious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall light, and the great vtilitie of the preſent Reformation: Doctorall promotions may likewiſe be made if the occaſion be offered.</p>
            <p>The other faculties are not hereby excluded, for it is likewiſe permitted vnto any of the Profeſſors to celebrate the great worke of the Almightie, and the continuance of his mercie this laſt hundred yeeres, in the name if their facultie.</p>
            <p>Finally, we are pleaſed, in our gracious good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that for the good imitation of others, this our Ordonance by publicke intimations, bee notified a moneth before, that ſo other Countries may receiue the knowledge thereof. If it pleaſe alſo ſome of our Diuines, to ſignifie vnto other ſincere Diuines, this our Chriſtian intention, and to admoniſh them, to conforme themſelues vnto this Action acceptable vnto God, we will in our fauour like well of it.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant by his grace, that wee, and all the Inhabitants of our Dominions, may performe this enſuing Feaſt of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> with good health, due atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hearty ioy in God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Datum</hi> Dreſden, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 12. <hi>of Auguſt,</hi> 1617.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Iohannes George, <hi>Churfurſt,</hi> that is, <hi>Prince Elector.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="chronology">
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:10"/>
            <head>A CHRONOLOGY OF THE GOSPELS IVBILEE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare 1517. the firſt wound was inflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon Antichriſt, in a diſputation at <hi>Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> againſt Indulgences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>refore doe Goſpellers Iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1518. the doctrine concerning iuſtification and the freewill of man was clearely explained in a diſputation at <hi>Heidelberge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1519. it was manifeſted in a ſolemne diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Lipſwicke,</hi> that there was no ſupremacie of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1520. <hi>Germanie</hi> began to laugh at, and to contemne the brutiſh thunderbolts or excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1521. the cauſe of the Goſpell was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at <hi>Wormes,</hi> before the Emperour and the whole Empire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1522. The Goſpell was propagated farre and wide through <hi>Germanie, Heluetia, Liuonia,</hi> or <hi>Liefe-land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6903:10"/>In the yeare 1523. the Popes Legate acknowledgeth in the diet of the Empire, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſicke with errors and vices, ſome places of <hi>Fraunce</hi> are illuſtrated with the light of the Goſpell, and the truth of it is ſealed with the bloud of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Zutphen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 2524. the Emperour, the Princes of the Empire, in an aſſembly in <hi>Stiria, Ferdinand, Henry</hi> the eight King of <hi>England, Lodowick</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bauaria and Loraine,</hi> the Pope, the Cardinall of <hi>Loraine,</hi> the Archbiſhops of <hi>Ments</hi> and <hi>Riga,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Denmarke, Spira,</hi> and <hi>Strauſburge,</hi> labour in vaine to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1525. amongſt the Countrey-inſurrections, the Contentions about the Sacraments, of the Anabaptiſts and of the Schwenkfeldians, the conſpiracies of the might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſt enemies againſt the Goſpell, the Goſpell took place in the kingdome of <hi>Sueuia,</hi> in the Dominion of the <hi>Lantſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue</hi> of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> and in a great part of <hi>Rhetia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1526. the Emperour, and the King of <hi>France</hi> being at contention amongſt themſelues through the Popes inſtigation againſt their will, they grant halcion dayes to the Church. The Emperor aboliſheth the authoritie of the Popes name through all <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1527. the Pope being taken the Engliſh and the French conſpiring againſt the Emperour doe miniſter occaſion to the Goſpellers of further ſpreading abroad the ſincere doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1528. the truth of the reformed doctrine triumph in the diſputation of <hi>Berne,</hi> vpon which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reformation of many famous Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The yeare 1529. is renouned for the reformation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches, and the vnconquered conſtancie of many Goſpellers in diuers trials, chiefely for the Martirdome of <hi>Lodowicke Berquinus</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of <hi>Clarebachius</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6903:11"/>
               <hi>Flidſtedius</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The yeare 1530. reioyceth profeſſors of the Goſpell for the confeſſion of their doctrine publickly made by the Princes at <hi>Ausberge,</hi> before the Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glorious, and almoſt miraculous deliuerance of the Proteſtants from a miſcheife hanging ouer their heads doth grace the yeare 1531.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The peace of Religion in <hi>Germany,</hi> the propagation of godly doctrine in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> the Martyrdomes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in <hi>England,</hi> doe make famous the yeare 1532.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glory of the yeare 1533. is exceeding great becauſe that therein the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhooke off the Popes yoake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1534. the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberge</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merania,</hi> hauing abandoned Popery embrace the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1535. the Churches of <hi>George</hi> Earle of <hi>Wirtemberge</hi> in <hi>Alſaſia</hi> are purged from the Popes leauen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> doth pull downe the Monaſteries in <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dennes of monſtrous villanies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1536. the Cittizens of <hi>Berne</hi> with their aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates doe make warre with the Duke of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> and doe take almoſt the whole Countrey of the <hi>Antuatum,</hi> by which victorie peace from the forreigne ennemie, is obtained to the common wealth and Church of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is ſpread all abroad through <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1537. The whole Kingdome of <hi>Denmarke</hi> hauing abandoned the Pope vnder the gouernement of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the third, acknowledged Chiſt to be the onely head of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the Goſpellers Iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1538. A publique Church is opened at <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge.</hi> to thoſe that were baniſhed from <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Belgia.</hi> It is determined in <hi>England,</hi> that the Bible being tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Engliſh tongue, be keept every where in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to be read by all that deſire it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1539. <hi>Miſnia,</hi> the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6903:11"/>
the Dukedome of <hi>Sagana</hi> in <hi>Sileſia</hi> and others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Poperie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the goſpellers Iubelize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1540. <hi>Robert Barnes D.</hi> of Divinitie, a man of great eſteeme with the King of <hi>England,</hi> being burnt to Aſhes by the Papiſts, taught not only the Engliſh his owne countrie-men, but all Chriſtians, to eſteeme leſſe even of their liues, than of the profeſſion of the true faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the Goſpellers Iubelize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1541. The <hi>Emperour</hi> by his priuate letters, granteth the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> the peace of religion. <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1542. <hi>Otto Henry,</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Rhene,</hi> Duke of either <hi>Bauaria,</hi> imbraceth the purer doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the Goſpellers Iubelize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1543. <hi>Hermanus</hi> Earle of <hi>Weda,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Colen</hi> applyed himſelfe to reforme the ſtate of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1544. the Pope being not regarded, the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nawerdenſes</hi> giue their names to Chriſt. <hi>Peter Alexander,</hi> Preacher to <hi>Mary</hi> Queene of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and Governeſſe of the <hi>Lowe-Countries,</hi> writteth and teacheth many things <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the Goſpellers Iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1545. <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> being a cruell enemy of the Reformed Religion, came into the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the <hi>Lantſgraue,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the Goſpellers Iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1546. <hi>Fredericke Elector Palatine</hi> doth bringe the Reformed Religion into the whole <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the Goſpellers doe Iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1547. when all things in <hi>Germanie</hi> ſeemed to be in a deſperate caſe, <hi>Edward</hi> (the Sonne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the Eight) King of <hi>England</hi> abrogats the <hi>MASSE,</hi> remoues Images out of the Temples, commaunds <hi>Bibles</hi> to be printed in the Vulgar tongue, miniſteriall duties to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the ſame tounge, both kinds to be adminiſtred in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe the &amp;.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1548. and 1549. during the time of the <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim,</hi> there is a ſifting of the Goſpellers, and the Hypocrites are diſcerned from ſincere Profeſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6903:12"/>In the yeere 1550. Maidenburg ſhewed a memorable example of Conſtancie, in defending the ſincerer Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1551. the Proteſtants are not afraid to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Tridentine Councell; the Papiſts not daring to heare the Reaſons of the reformed Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1552. the moſt conſtant Confeſſors of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn Fredericke</hi> Elector of Saxonie, and <hi>Philip</hi> Lantſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue of Haſſia, beeing freed from captiuitie are ſent home: the Paſſauian peace is eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1553. at Lyons in France nine Students confirmed the veritie of the reformed Doctrine by bloodie Martyrdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1554. the Cities and Nobles of Greichgoia hold a Synode, wherin they renounce the <hi>Interim,</hi> and bind themſelues to teach, and heare the purer Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1555. it is decreed in the Diet at Ausburg, that they ſhould not make warre with any Prince, Earle or Imperiall Citie for the doctrine of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1556. <hi>Charles</hi> Marqueſſe of Baden, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Churches vnder his iuriſdiction according to the preſcript of Gods word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1557. <hi>Otto Henricus</hi> Count Palatine Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, doth the ſecond time purge the Churches of the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, from Popiſh Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1558. the Nobles of Scotland purge the Churches of Sterlin from all Maſſing ſtuffe, and appoint Preachers of the Goſpel in townes here and there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1559. All England, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being queene
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6903:12"/>
thereof, doth the ſecond time receiue the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1560. the French men preſent the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their faith to the King: the Nobles of Scotland reiect the Maſſe, demoliſh Altars, and aboliſh Images.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1561. the Princes and States Proteſtants in Germany, being gathered together at Naumburg, renue their conſent to the Apoſtolicke Faith, againſt the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt of Rome: the Frecnh of the Reformed Religion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the chiefe Heads of the pure Faith, in the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at Poiſſy, before the King and the whole kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yere 1562. God diſappointed the dangerous plots of the <hi>Guyzes,</hi> tending to bring the French Churches into the hatred of the Germaine Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1563. an Edict publiſhed the 19. of March, graunteth peace of Religion to the reformed Churches in Fraunce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yere 1564. the Proteſtant Princes and Magiſtrates firmely demonſtrate by many Arguments, that the Triden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Councell was neither godly, nor lawfull, nor free: and conſequently not to be receiued with a ſafe conſcience: That Antichriſt was Preſident there, and that errors quite contrarie to the holy Scripture were maintained therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1565. <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour ſhewed himſelfe fauourable to the Goſpellers of Sileſia, Morauia, Bohemia, Auſtria, Hungaria, and graunteth the Magiſtrates of Gorlick, that the Monaſterie of the Minorites being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a publike Schoole, they may take order, that both humane Learning, and alſo the purer Doctrine of Religion be taught there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1566. in Brabant, Holland, Zeeland, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6903:13"/>
Flanders, the idolatrous Images of the Papiſts are caſt downe, the Popiſh Religion remooued, and the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in many places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1567. <hi>Fredericke</hi> the 3. Count Palatine Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, aboliſheth popiſh Rites in the Palatinate of Bauarie, <hi>Ioachimus Fredericus,</hi> Marquis of Brandenburg, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Archbiſhopricke of Magdeburg, doth open the Cathedrall Church of Magdeburg, that had bin ſhut vp al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 20. yeeres, and commends it to the Preachers of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1568. <hi>Maximilian</hi> the 2. Emperour, grants the Nobilitie of Auſtria, the free exerciſe of the purer Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1569. <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of Brunswicke, taketh order, that the Churches which are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his iuriſdiction be religiouſly reformed according to the rule of Gods word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1570. In France it is graunted by the kings Edict, that the Princes, Barons, and Nobles in their terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, that others in certaine Countries, and ſuburbes may vſe the exerciſe of the reformed Religion without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1571. Peace beeing made the third time in Fraunce, a Synode of the reformed Churches of the whole Kingdome, is aſſembled at Rochel; in which, the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faith of the French Churches is repeated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1572. that bloodie Maſſacre at Paris, was a moſt pregnant argument to the reformed Churches, that the Papiſts deſpaired of the cauſe of the Romiſh Religion, ſeeing they deemed it could not bee maintained by holy Scripture, but by incredible trecherie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1573. the number of the Proteſtants growes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6903:13"/>
exceeding great, out of the blood of thoſe of the reformed Religion that were cruelly ſlaine, and that beyond the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of the King, the Pope, and all Papiſts, Rochel by the wonderfull prouidence of God, is deliuered from the duke of Aniou, as once <hi>Dauid</hi> was from <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1574. Middleburg in Zeland is taken by Compoſition: Leyden in Holland is miraculouſly deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from a ſiege.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1575. in the midſt of the warres of the lowe Countries, the Vniuerſitie of Leyden is ſet open by the munificencie of the States of Holland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1576. the order of Baptiſing with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of viſiting the ſicke, is ſet foorth at Venice: In which booke the doctrine of the free iuſtification of a ſinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, is clearely propounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1577. the agreement betweene profeſſours of both Religions in the Low-countries, is ſworne at Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1578. Amſterdam the moſt famous Mart-towne of Holland, is reformed according to the rule of Gods word, the Romiſh Religion baniſhed, and Images de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1579. the vnion of Vtrecht is made by meanes of <hi>Iohn</hi> Eearle of Naſſau then Gouernour of Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derland and Sutphen, he reſtored ſome moſt famous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of the Low-Countries to the libertie of the purer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1580. the towneſmen of Deuenter, they of Swool, of Vtrecht, of Freezland, and of Drenth, breake downe Images, and forſake the Romiſh religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1581. The exerciſe of the Popiſh religion is forbidden at Antwerpe and Bruxels by a publike Edict.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1582. <hi>Gebhardus</hi> Archbiſhop of Collen, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of the Empire, doth aſſay the reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6903:14"/>In the yeere 1583. the Churches of France do flouriſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the thornes of diuers perſecutions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1584. The conſpiracie of certaine Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men againſt the life and State of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> begun at the inſtigation of the Pope, is diſcouered by the ſingular goodneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1585. the Kingdomes of France, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre learne to contemne excommunications of Pope <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> the fift, againſt <hi>Henry</hi> king of Nauarre, and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of Condee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1586. at Luneburg <hi>Fredericke</hi> king of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, the Ambaſſadors of the Q. of England and of <hi>Iames</hi> king of Scotland, the Electors of Empire <hi>Iohn Caſimirus</hi> Adminiſtrator Palatine, Chriſtian Elector of Saxonie, <hi>Iohn Georgius</hi> Elector of Brandenburg, and other Princes of the Empire, wiſely conſidering that the troubles in France concerned the Germane Churches, agreed to ayde the king of Nauarre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1587. the holy league betweene the Pope and certaine popiſh Princes, is renued in vaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1588.</p>
            <q>
               <l>With ſhips ſans number bridging all the Maine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spaniards</hi> preſume they'l <hi>Brittaine</hi> ioyne to <hi>Spaine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wouldſt know the moouing cauſes of ſuch ſtirs?</l>
               <l>The proud, <hi>Ambition</hi> driues, and <hi>Auarice</hi> ſpurs.</l>
               <l>How fit by winds was puft <hi>Ambition</hi> drown'd?</l>
               <l>And ſwelling waues the ſwelling ſunke to ground:</l>
               <l>How fit did ſwallowing gulfes of Seas ne're drie,</l>
               <l>Swallow vp the <hi>Helluo's</hi> of Worlds Seigniorie?</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the yeere 1589. the king of France makes a league with the king of Nauarre, and makes him Lieutenant ouer his armies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1590. <hi>Iames</hi> Marqueſſe of Baden ſonne of-<hi>Charles,</hi> an Apoſtate, dieth of the blooudie fluxe, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning of the perſecution againſt them of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, the doctrine of the Goſpel is preſerued in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6903:14"/>
that part of the Marquiſtate, to the great griefe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The yeeres from 1591. euen till the truce of Spaine with the Low-countries (which happened in the yeere 1608.) are ennobled, by reaſon of the almoſt continuall victories of the Hollanders againſt the Spaniards: that is, of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers againſt the Papiſts: thefore in regard of all thoſe yeeres,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>the Goſpellers doe iubilize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1608. Libertie of Religion in Bohemia, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia, and Hungaria, was eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeere 1569. and 1610. <hi>William</hi> Duke of Gulicke being dead, the word of God is freely preached, by the permiſſion of the Princes, through the Dukedomes of Bergh, of Cleue, and Gulicke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the yeere 1610. to the yeere 1617. the Churches through France, Germany, England, Scotland, Denmarke, Suetia, Polonia, Hungaria, Bohemia, haue had, and at this day haue reaſonable Halcion dayes, Antichriſt in vaine withſtanding them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore doe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to thee moſt High and mighty God, with a deuoted heart they giue thanks, that amongſt thoſe ragings of the Ieſuites, amongſt ſo many perſecutions of the Romane Antichriſt, thou doſt notwithſtanding gather to thy ſelfe a Church amongſt vs, wherein thou art both truely acknowledged, and alſo art worſhipped, according to the preſcript of thy Word. Bleſſed be thy holy Name for euer and euer. Goe forward O God, to bleſſe the Vine which thou haſt planted in ſo many king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Dominions, Countries, Cities,: And graunt that wee drawing from Chriſt alone the ſappe of true conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bringing foorth the fruit of a holy life through him alone, may for euer adhere vnto our Sauiour Chriſt, euen as branches to the Vine. Keepe vnder Ieſuites, the bellowes of Sathan, leſt they continue to make ciuill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, and trouble the peace of thy Church. Leade and gouerne the hearts of thy faithful ones in the ſpirit of vnity, that we may all be one, as thou art one, and ſanctifie vs in thy truerh, thy word is Truth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:6903:15"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <p>AS before their is a remarkeable example of the exceeding goodnes of God, in glorifiyng the Goſpell of his welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sonne, by the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Spalato</hi> his renouncing of Antichriſt, and forſaking his Primacy Eccleſiasticall ouer two Kingdomes for the truth ſake, where by the period of the firſt hundred yeares; after <hi>Luther</hi> had ſet vp his <hi>Propoſitions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tho Popes pardons, was gloriouſly ſhut up: So it is thought convenient to commend to thy godly conſideration the great, and good worke of our gracious God, the God of Truth, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing his Truth this yeare <hi>1618.</hi> being the firſt of the ſecond hundred yeares, by diſcovering the treaſon of <hi>Barneuil,</hi> and his <hi>Arminian</hi> complices tending to the great impeachment of the ſame. By delivering up a principall inſtrument in the ſame to a reprobate minde, ſo as he murthered himſelfe, after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the treaſon, by rayſing vp that <hi>Worthy in Iſrael, Graue Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> with admirable policy, diligence, and peace to purge <hi>Arminian</hi> townes of corrupt, and dangerous Magiſtrats, and to Re-unite Provinces and Cities, which were upon the poynt of <hi>Confuſion</hi> ſo preuayling was the diuliſh poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Arminian</hi> heriſy; and by ſanctifiyng the minds of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>States,</hi> in a moſt religious manner, to call togither the preſent Nationall <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Dorte.</hi> Whereby, through Gods bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame, <hi>Truth</hi> may be cleared, <hi>Wiſedome</hi> iuſtified, and the <hi>Goſpell</hi> haue a freer paſſage. Which God graunt for his great Names ſake: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6903:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
